[MUSIC]
Hello, hi.
Hi everybody.
We are having a game scheduled at this stage right now.
If you want to stay and play the game, it's going to be in English.
So we're going to start very soon.
If you want to stay, you're welcome to stay.
If you don't want to stay, you can also stay and hang out.
And the game is called Gnomic.
It's not like any other game you've played.
It's going to blow your mind.
You're going to want to tell everybody about this game.
Especially if you are a nerd in law or it's going to be fun.
And the fundamental idea of this game is about changing rules.
So you make the rules of the game.
So can I have a show of hands who's going to stay and join the game?
Yeah, yeah.
If you want to stay and join the game, would you come closer and take a chair or bench and come closer?
Because that will involve a bit of talking.
So if you want to stay and play the game, please come closer to me and sit in a circle.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
I mean, come closer if you want.
It's better that everybody sits in a circle if you want to join the game.
You can continue eating, having your lunch.
Wow.
A alpaca.
Nice.
Great.
All good?
Everybody who's going to join the game?
Nice.
So I have the rules. There's an initial set of rules that I have it on an online notepad.
That if you want to look at it on your own device, you're welcome to scan the QR code.
I think that will give you access, the viewing access to the notepad.
Which I will -- oh, sorry.
I think -- which I will show on a screen as well.
But in case you want to have a reference in your hand, you're welcome to scan the QR code.
Does it work?
Yes.
Good, great. Awesome.
So I have the editing rights to the pad.
And the fundamental idea of the game is that every move every player plays is a suggestion of changing the rules.
Okay?
So every one of you, every player of you will participate by making suggestions to change the rules of the game.
And there are two sets of rules, two types of rules to begin with.
One is immutable rules, which means immutable -- mutable means -- oh, okay.
Mutable means that you are able to change.
Immutable rules means that they are not -- you cannot change it.
But you can make suggestions to move it to mutable rules.
Then you can change it.
Do you understand?
What does it mean?
Okay.
So this is the mutable rules.
And this is the immutable rules.
Okay?
So these -- the rules in the category of immutable rules, you are not able to change them to begin with.
Question.
So which rules are immutable?
Here we can see the ones that begin with one, 101, these are immutable rules.
And the ones that begin with two are mutable rules.
Okay?
So what it means is that when we start playing, if you want to change the rule of 101, you first have to suggest that we move 101 to the second box, which is here, 20.
Question?
Do you understand?
So everything that starts with one are immutable rules, and they cannot be changed directly.
You cannot say, oh, I want to change one or something.
But in the box of 201, they are mutable rules, and you can suggest to change them directly.
For example, this rule that says one turn takes no more than three minutes, you can suggest to change it to one turn takes up to five minutes, let's say.
Okay?
But if it is in the number of one or something, whatever is in there, you have to say, okay, now we move them into this box before changing them.
Does it make sense?
Do you understand?
Great.
Okay. If you have any question, please ask at any moment.
Yes.
Question?
The game.
What is the goal of the game?
That is the best question.
Exactly.
What is the goal of the game?
Normally, what is the goal of a game?
Why do you play a game?
To win.
Right?
What does it say right now in this game, in the initial set of rules?
Does it say anything about winning?
Do you see a rule?
Yes.
Which one?
What does it say?
Yes.
And it is in the box of mutable rules.
Right?
What does it mean?
It can be changed.
It could be 50 points.
And think wilder.
Does it have to be points?
It could be anything.
Exactly.
What could it be?
What would you like to have?
You can have five alpacas.
Or make a suggestion.
You can define the rules.
You are right.
You can change the rules.
Exactly.
The first person who wears a heart rock hoodie.
Could it be?
If you make the suggestion to change the rules and everybody votes for you, then yes, then you win.
Do you get it now?
What is the point of the game then?
Yes.
What are the points?
Yeah.
The rules are 100 points.
Oh, they are rules about points.
Exactly.
They are rules of points.
But they are in the mutable box.
Which means?
They can be changed.
Does the game end?
What do you think?
It doesn't say now in the current set of rules.
Can it be said?
We can change it.
Yes.
Of course.
One more time.
This is the bar code of the existing set of rules.
If you want to have the reference on your device.
That is the same as what is displayed on the screen right now.
You kind of need the device.
Yes.
You kind of need it.
I will need some help with documenting the points.
First of all, or do we do it on the honor system that everybody writes down their own points?
And keep track of their own points?
What do you suggest?
What do you prefer?
Or do you want to have a public board that I display on the screen?
Okay.
Which means then we will have to ask for everybody's name.
And --
Yes.
Exactly.
Okay.
Now, last step before we start the most awesome game of all games.
We are going to go through all the rules we have right now.
Okay.
So this is just the rules I wrote up from also previous players.
And you have a loose set of rules that you can begin with.
And now we can -- can we read it out one by one?
Yeah.
Muteable rules.
You can go louder.
All rules change proposed in the proper way shall be voted on.
They will be adopted if and only if they receive the required number of votes.
102.
Every player is an eligible voter.
Every eligible voter must participate in every vote on rule change.
Great.
So some terms that are a bit more formal, if you don't understand, please ask.
Okay?
103.
No rule change may take effect earlier than the moment the completion of the vote that adopted it.
Even if it is wording explicitly states otherwise.
No rule change may have re-created application.
104.
Each proposed rule change shall be given a rank or the number or the number of the reference.
The numbers shall begin with 301.
And each rule change proposed in the proper way shall receive the next successive integer,
whether or not the proposal is adopted.
[SIDE CONVERSATION]
106.
107.
[SIDE CONVERSATION]
108.
You're not playing?
Okay.
Are you playing?
[SIDE CONVERSATION]
Oh, okay.
It's also on the screen.
[SIDE CONVERSATION]
Go ahead.
A negative vote.
[SIDE CONVERSATION]
109.
Whatever is not.
Explicitly.
[SIDE CONVERSATION]
Implicitly.
Does it make sense?
What does it mean?
Do you understand it?
[SIDE CONVERSATION]
Nice.
Okay.
[SIDE CONVERSATION]
Now, okay, so another set, mutable rules.
201.
[SIDE CONVERSATION]
202.
That's a very important word.
Unanimous.
Do you know what that means?
[SIDE CONVERSATION]
Yes.
Unanimous vote means that everybody has to vote for it.
[SIDE CONVERSATION]
207.
I will have to ask you to move to the back.
Yeah.
And also you.
If you're not participating in the game, may I ask you to move to the back?
Okay.
You're charging.
[SIDE CONVERSATION]
You don't understand that means that you cannot talk to each other about what rule you're going to make unless you're teammates.
Other teams?
How do you create a team?
Currently I have no teammates I guess.
Currently you don't have any teammates.
Exactly.
You might have to make a rule about how to create teammates.
[SIDE CONVERSATION]
Precedence.
That means the lower number of the rule will be followed.
Alright.
Is there any question at this stage after we've read all the rules we have on hand right now?
Do you get everything?
Great.
And now we're escorting our two young gentlemen to the back of the room.
Is this okay when they...
Do you want to join?
No?
Okay.
Alright.
Now that everybody is ready for the game, and we shall start.
Great.
Do you remember how to start?
Okay.
Let's say the youngest.
We'll start from the youngest.
The youngest hacker in the room.
Are you the youngest?
David?
Yeah?
14?
Anybody younger than 14?
No.
Okay.
14.
David, you start.
You can either suggest to move anything from one or something to two or something from the immutable rules to mutable rules, or you can suggest a new rule.
Or you can say delete one rule. That's also fine. Or you can say modify any of the existing rules.
Yeah, you can say anything. Like from the 200 box.
And I will make a timer because in case that you will take forever to decide, I will make a three minute timer.
I will change rule 209.
You will change rule 209 to?
More than 100.
Great.
100? You sure? Okay.
All right.
Yeah, so everything that comes now will start from 300.
Yes, because once you change it, that one is gone.
Yes.
All right. Now, remember how to get a rule passed at this stage? What do we need?
Yeah, we need to vote on it. And every player needs to vote on it. And we need a, what kind of vote?
A unanimous vote. We need a unanimous vote to get it passed. Okay?
So now, let's vote on it.
Who is for to change rule 209 to 100 mutable rules?
Okay, we have one against it. So immediately it doesn't get passed.
So yeah, another, yeah, exactly. So another rule we have is that we need to alternate in clockwise order, which gives us you.
Okay, then I would like to propose to change rule 203.
203?
I would like to change it to if and only if the vote is a majority. So we no longer have to, everyone agree on a rule change, but we would have to basically the majority has to vote for it, and then a rule gets accepted. So we would change to a democracy from a consent-based system.
Okay.
Correct? Is this how you want to phrase it?
Yes, this is important. So a rule change is adopted if and only if the majority of the eligible voters vote in favor of the change.
Vote, vote.
Now we have to vote. Does everybody vote pass? Yes. Okay, gets adopted. Nice.
Now you can roll a dice, which is here.
You can start rolling and then.
Wait, what do you want?
Can I roll a bigger dice?
Yeah, which one?
Which one?
I mean I could roll a 100 sided dice.
No. Okay.
And then you can say start, I'll click roll.
Oh, you get 16.
Okay.
I didn't get, that's true.
Say start.
You got a three.
Okay, so now we can see in the set of mutable rules, which means that things can be changed, that rule number 203 is changed to rule 2301.
Now it becomes a rule change is adopted if and only if the majority of the eligible voters vote in favor of the change.
And right now we have one, two, three, four, five, six, seven, eight voters and players.
If we have more than four votes, then we get a rule passed.
Okay.
Great.
Next one.
We have one more player coming back.
All right. Okay. Do you want to.
Should we.
We skipped you last. Okay.
Do you want to jump back in?
Right. Okay.
Yeah, we don't have to change the rules to allow that. We can just go ahead and do that.
Yeah.
Okay, now.
My name.
Amy.
EMEA.
Email.
Cool.
Do you want to make a suggestion?
Email. Email. Yes.
You want to create a new rule?
Which is?
Okay.
Do we have something like that?
We do not currently have any restrictions, so this is a new rule. At no time may there be more than 15 immutable rules.
Okay.
And now vote.
We have one, two, three, four, five, six, seven. Pass.
Okay, now we have.
So there is a rule that says.
If and when rule changes can be adopted without unanimity, the players who vote against winning proposals shall receive 10 points apiece.
So that means you receive 10 points.
Yeah.
But before that, we need to roll the dice for email.
Wow, you get 20.
Nice.
And what's your name?
Timo.
Timo?
T-I-M-O.
And you get.
Do you remember how many?
10 points just by being contrarian.
Correct.
So what do we do in that case?
But when you're playing, right?
So you can create a rule that states that the player is present because someone who's not present is not a player.
Not eligible to vote. I guess we need to roll.
I mean, I guess we can discuss.
The team, whatever a team is, we still don't know what a team is.
But I guess we have to find what a team is, that we are also violating anything.
Oh, no, we are violating this. We're just allowed to discuss something if we're teammates.
We have to find that, right?
Good point.
How do we resolve this?
We don't have a rule on that yet.
A conflict.
Is there a conflict if there isn't a rule?
Good question.
Can we?
Your turn.
First, what's your name?
Monica.
And Monica, it's your turn.
So based on the discussions earlier, what do other players want and what do you want?
There can be teams.
That's a new rule. There can be teams.
Each turn?
Each turn.
So every time a new player says something, that's each turn.
One round.
One round is one from the first player finishing until the last player and then starts again from the first player.
That will be one round.
It needs to stop until you're back.
Or maybe the round.
Or am I not allowed to leave it?
It means that if you're in a team, then your teammate can go in your group and get a double vote.
How big is the team?
Each round, everyone stays with whom he wants to be in.
So there can be more rules if there's a conflict.
So you basically say I want to be in a team with you and you?
Are we still discussing the problem of leaving and coming back?
No, just of teams.
I didn't make a proposal just for leaving and coming back.
Okay, now you have to finalize your rule.
Here, new players, if you want to join, please come over here.
Yeah.
Yeah, I can put up the QR code again.
This is the QR code of the rule set with the rule book that we're going with right now.
You already scanned it?
Cool.
All right, Monica, now let's get back to you.
Finalize your rule.
Yes.
Okay, we'll leave some ambiguity.
This is how you want the rule to be?
Okay.
Is this the form you want to be voted upon?
Now, every player, time to vote.
Okay, if you vote for, please stand up.
Okay, we have four votes.
No, that's not enough.
I'm afraid that is not passed.
That is not passed, so.
However, who was against?
David was against.
Sorry?
Oh, that's true.
You're right.
It's not a winning proposal.
My bad.
Your dice.
I get 11.
Your turn.
May I know your name?
Hannah.
Okay.
Let's see.
Hannah, what have you got?
A new rule.
It's also about creating teams.
Yes.
Okay.
Right.
One player's team up.
Okay, all teammates.
I don't know how to use this keyboard.
His points double.
And their votes shall be consistent.
Their votes, meaning that they have to vote on the same thing.
Oh, okay.
Yeah, okay.
So each teammate gets two votes.
Okay.
So, Hannah, you're suggesting a new rule.
One player's team up.
Each teammate gets two votes.
And their votes shall be consistent.
Must be.
Must be consistent.
Are there any questions?
Confusions?
Very confused.
Is there a question answered?
What is it?
What's the answer?
Yes.
Hannah?
Okay.
So one player's team up.
Correct.
All right.
Every player, time to vote.
One, two, three, four, five, six.
All right.
So it gets passed.
Now we have a new rule.
One player's team up.
Their votes must be consistent.
And each teammate gets two votes.
Each player's voted against gets ten points.
Could you, yes.
Emil, do you have a question?
Good point.
Very good point.
Exactly.
That's a very good point.
Yes.
Now my rule is voted on.
I can't change it.
For the next person.
Yeah.
Great.
As for the points, I think both of us, we lost our suggestion for a change.
And I think we then have minus points, right?
Exactly.
You should have minus points.
So that was minus ten.
Who can tell me how to, okay.
Okay.
So if you propose a rule suggestion and it loses, you get minus ten points.
But if you vote against a rule that is then decided to come into place, then you get plus ten.
Okay.
Yes.
So at the moment, the --
All good?
Yes.
Very good?
I love the rules.
Amazing.
I'm glad you love the rules.
Do you want to join the game?
Great.
Our chef is going to come back.
You want to come on stage?
Oh.
This one?
Yes.
Okay.
There you go.
Yeah.
There are some very devoted fans for the game.
So just as a reminder that at the moment, in mutable rules, we have some rules about the point system.
One being, as Alex has suggested, that if you're a contrarian against the majority, then you are incentivized because, you know, not every -- not to say majority always have the best idea in mind for everybody.
Right?
So maybe this rule is not good, and you vote against it, but it still gets passed, but you will receive ten points just because you're against it.
I have a question.
Do we have a rule about when you can still change your vote so if, like, thumbs go up and you see, oh, there's a majority, you turn your thumb down?
Good point.
Maybe someone is cheating.
We don't have it yet, but you may think about it.
It's not cheating if there's no rule.
Exactly.
Maybe it's not cheating.
That's very true.
Very good points.
And another rule we have at the moment about points is that 206, when a proposed rule change is defeated, the player who proposed it loses ten points.
And 103, right, says that no rule -- yeah, so basically 103 says that no rule changed comes into effect before the vote is completed, which basically means that you can change your vote throughout because it just changes, like, the moment the vote is done.
So the voting counts in that moment.
Yes.
So vote as late as possible.
I guess.
Shall we continue?
Not yet.
Because Hannah hasn't rolled a dice.
Oh, yeah.
There you are.
We're going to roll the dice for you.
Six.
And also before that, before we proceed, the people who voted against Hannah's rule will receive ten points. That includes you.
What's your name?
Sven.
Sven?
Okay.
Sven gets ten points.
Did you vote against it?
Yes.
Okay. You also get ten points.
Timo is a serial contrarian.
And --
It is rule number -- 204.
It was.
It was voted by majority.
It was adopted.
It's just not valid because there's a rule with a lower number that says a different thing, but it's in the rule set.
Yes.
Adopted meaning that it is being part of the rules now.
No, we have six people with thumbs up.
It was majority vote.
Any confusions or misunderstanding?
Nothing against this for this turn?
Yes?
I also voted against it.
You voted against it.
That was -- okay, let's go again.
Come again.
You voted for it, right?
And Hannah voted for it.
And Emil, you voted for it.
You didn't.
You voted against it.
You voted for it.
So that was six votes.
And, yeah, they all voted for it.
But you also get ten points.
You voted against it.
Emil as well.
Both of you get ten points.
Okay.
Now it is Sven's turn.
Sven.
I would like to go back to the rule 102 problem.
Okay.
Before you continue, remember there is a very fundamental rule that it is 102 is an immutable rule.
Which means that you have to move it to --
I don't want to change the rule.
I want to create a rule that defines what a player is.
Okay.
You want to define what a player is.
Exactly.
Which means you want to add a new rule.
In a mutable rule box.
In the standard mutable rule box.
Exactly.
You have to be very precise.
I'll try to be.
Great.
Therefore, we have rule 304.
That says a player is --
Propose a player is only a person present at the voting can be a player.
Is a person present is and only is a person present at the voting round.
The vote.
At the vote.
I have a question.
You can leave at any time.
But if you are not present for a vote, you will just be skipped.
You are not a player at that moment.
We can't really do anything.
Technically.
Well, yes.
But it still says in one or two that every player must vote on every rule.
Is there a rule that I'm proposing?
Okay.
Any more questions?
Sven is proposing a new rule.
Every player.
A player is and only is a person present at the vote.
Is this clear?
Okay.
What is that?
Thumbs up.
Up.
One, two, three, four, five, six, seven.
We have seven, four.
Yeah.
So I have ten players right now and seven votes for the change.
And you get the rule passed.
Congratulations.
Thank you.
You write a new rule, Sven.
At the same time, we have three against it.
Right?
Alex and Timal.
Serial contrarian, huh?
So you get ten.
David get ten.
Alex get ten.
And now Sven, you roll the dice.
13.
And we're going back to the rules.
Now we have a new rule that says a player is and only is a person present at the vote.
Okay?
Good.
Now moving on to the next turn, Timal.
Finally, your turn.
What are you going to do?
A new rule, please.
Okay.
If players are not on the seat or not involved in the game during the voting phase, the votes will be divided equally between the two results.
In the event of a tie, however, the votes will not be continued.
Again.
A little slower.
If a player is not on their seat during the vote, then that's not a player.
The vote will be divided equally between the two results.
In the event of a tie, however, the votes will not be counted.
Your vote will be evenly divided.
I think you have to explain it a bit more.
It does not because it is contrary to the previous rule.
Okay.
Oh, thank you.
If players -- if a player is not on their -- or not involved in the game, are not involved in the game during the voting phase, their vote will be divided.
Will be divided between the two results.
Okay.
In the event of a tie, however, the votes will not be counted.
Do I get this?
Does it make any difference?
Exactly.
It doesn't matter.
Timo doesn't care.
I had no time to think.
Timo has no time to -- you have time to think.
You can think right now.
No, you refuse to think.
Okay.
It's different.
It's not that you don't have time to think.
You refuse to think.
Okay.
Timo refuses to think.
As a serial contrarian, he refuses to think.
Can he even refuse his own rule in his voting?
Being a serial contrarian, I think he will.
We can make a rule that says Timo is not allowed to vote against things.
We totally can do that.
You totally can do that.
I cannot.
Is there any clarification needs to be made?
Any questions?
Frage?
Confusion?
Dismissal?
Any -- anything?
Okay.
No more questions?
Shall we begin the vote?
Okay.
Let's vote on Timo's proposal.
Rule 305, if a player is not on their seat or not involved in a game during the voting phase,
their vote will be divided between the two results.
In the event of a tie, however, the votes will not be counted.
Great.
All right.
The rule is not voted for, and hence we're going to delete it.
Okay.
We can keep it in.
We can do that.
It also says rule 104 says that each rule change proposed shall receive the next integer,
whether or not the proposal is adopted.
So we need to keep record of the rules.
Correct.
We need to keep it.
So we need to keep the number as well.
Dice for Timo.
Yay.
13.
All right.
Now our new player.
Okay.
Do you want to continue playing or do you want to -- you can make changes to the previous rules.
You can say --
Continue to be present.
And just say you can also delete any of the rules, existing rules.
I have an idea.
You have an idea.
Teams can be made --
Okay.
When one person asks a yes or no question and every person that says yes is a team and
every person that says no is a team, I think it would spice things up basically.
I think that's a different rule.
I don't know.
I don't think the mic likes me.
You're overthinking.
Point it towards the speaker.
Yeah.
Okay.
Wait a second.
I just need -- I think this is -- the computer is frozen.
I'm just going to listen to my friend's voice memo real quick.
I'll be right back.
You will be right back.
Okay.
Can someone --
In 20 seconds.
Okay.
Finalize the rule.
Good points.
What is it?
Can we form?
By asking a yes/no -- painful.
Sorry.
I don't know how to type on the German keyword.
Yes/no question.
Interesting.
Okay.
And everybody?
And everybody says yes.
Okay.
You have to talk to each other.
I'm not my role to get involved.
I'm just going to ask you to talk to each other.
Okay.
I'm going to ask you to talk to each other.
You voted against it again, right?
And what's your name?
Dimi.
D-I-M-I.
Exactly.
Yes.
Great.
You get 10 points as well.
And Lily, you get to roll the dice.
Where did the dice go?
Do I close it?
Yeah, here.
Okay.
Say start.
I'm going to roll the dice.
Okay.
Say start.
Start.
Four.
Okay.
You get four.
Any other thing I'm missing?
Who gets a point?
Okay.
All right.
So now we're going back to Dimi.
Dimi, you're finishing the round.
Empower.
Come on.
I would create a new rule for...
Dimi is going to create a new rule?
Team making because currently...
Not team making, the lifespan of teams.
Wow.
The lifespan of teams.
I think with the current mechanism of creating a team, it would be the best if a team would
only be valid for one round because there are these questions.
The thing is these questions, 306, I don't ask if I understand it correctly.
206.
Because in 202, there stands that first a rule is proposed and then a die is rolled,
but not that these questions are asked.
I hope you understand what I mean.
I do not.
Perfect.
Does everybody understand what he means?
We didn't amend 202 yet.
No.
Could I maybe, instead of create a new rule, change 202?
Yeah.
Then I would add as a first point that happens even before proposing a new rule that these
yes/no questions for the teams get asked.
Is this optional or do you have to?
Are you suggesting a change to 306?
To what?
306.
No, 202.
Yeah, 202.
That first...
Okay, so you want to move, basically you want to move 306 to 202.
Basically I want to include 306 into 202.
Yes.
That...
Which is different from what you said earlier about the lifespan of the team.
Yes, it's different.
I had a new idea.
Okay, you have a new idea.
Dimitri has an idea to incorporate 306 into 202.
So instead of making a proposal that it is a compulsory...
Yeah.
But then that means that...
I think it would be nice if it is mandatory, so you must, as the very first step of each
round, you must ask a yes/no question to both teams to spice it up.
To spice it up.
That's a good reason.
That's a very good reason.
This is exactly what the game is for.
We need more spice.
It's too bland at the moment.
I'm bored.
Okay, but that means you have to think about the consequence of that, is that each turn
there will be a new team forming.
Yes.
Right?
Okay.
He can edit just 202, and in the edit he adds basically what's set in 206, and adds,
for example, the lifespan also to the things he's adding to 202.
It's part of it, yeah.
So one turn takes no more than three minutes, consists of three parts in this order that
you first have the player at their turn
and generate teams by asking a yes/no maybe question.
Must generate teams by asking.
And each one must answer, and they are allowed to lie.
Each team.
But then you don't have to formulate the lifespan of the team because automatically at every
new turn new teams are formed.
We have a team meeting theme for our Jugend-Tek group, a small group of a few people every
day to this time, and then we would go away for a few minutes, a few minutes, and our players
this time, sorry.
Should we make an intermission of the game?
Do you want to finish your role first?
Yes.
So first you have to ask a yes/no question to generate a team.
Then the original steps of 202 would come proposing one rule change and having it voted
on.
And then the throwing one die once and adding the number of points on its face to one score.
Yes.
That would be the new proposal.
Okay let's vote.
One, two, three, four, five, six, seven.
Okay your rule gets passed.
Great so now we have 202.
This gets written over.
Okay.
Okay now shall we continue or do you want to break?
Continue?
Vote?
We need a majority vote for this.
Do you want to continue?
Or we need a unanimous vote for this?
Yeah like the game is on pause right now.
A ten minute break.
We'll meet here at ten two three.
Okay we'll meet back here at ten two three.
The slot is until four.
Until four.
But my suggestion is that now we take a ten minute break and when we come back please
spice up the game.
Right I think Lily has a very very good point.
That it has to be fun.
Yeah okay.
Alright I do I can check here.
Yes.
Okay.
[ Silence ]