[MUSIC]
>> Good evening. Hello.
Good evening. Hello.
Welcome to Millie Boys.
The evening talks at Millie Boys on day three.
I hope you had a great day already and we'll have
a much greater day in the evening today with nice talks.
The next talk will be
held by the network team of the Tor project.
They will present us with
a guided tour through Tor networking,
health, and performance.
>> Thanks everybody for coming.
We have collected a little group of people from the Tor project here,
who's going to talk a bit about general network status thing,
and particularly with focus on the health and
the performance that we've been working a lot on in the past few years.
I'll just do a quick introduction of everybody.
I'm Alex. I'm heading up towards network team.
We're the team responsible for writing the C Tor implementation
and the Rust implementation that we'll be talking a little bit about called RD.
Then we also have Yuka on stage.
Yuka is one of our bandwidth scanning experts and work together with
Geog who is the network health team lead.
Finally, we have Gus who's heading up our community team and
is doing a lot of the engagement with people in our community,
and the relay operating community and so forth.
If we start out with talking a bit about some of the features we've been working on
for the currently stable Tor release called 047.
One of the things we built in that was congestion control.
Tor had originally not had any good mechanisms like we see in TCP,
with regards to congestion control and handling congestion in the network,
which led to a higher variance in error conditions when you were using Tor
and the performance was not so good.
What the team did was that we evaluated a number of different options
for congestion control algorithm.
People who are into some of these TCP things might notice some of the names are similar.
They're very related from the general network world.
The three system we looked at was called Westwood and Vegas and NOLA.
While the team was looking at it, Google also came with a paper
with a congestion control system called BBR.
But many of these systems suffered from some issues that led to these runaway congestion conditions
which made them unsuitable for what we were trying to do.
We ended up spending a lot of time working in a simulator that we have called Shadow,
where we tried to test the different algorithms for seeing how they were performing,
having an idea about which parameters we could tune in various conditions,
and see how things are doing.
These plots are a little bit difficult to understand.
They're CDF plots, but the idea here is that the orange part of the curve is the 047 release
and the blue part is the 046 release.
And the left picture is a simulated instance where we tried to behave
like we're a client being in Germany, and on the right-hand side we see one in Hong Kong.
And what basically these things tell is that we see a higher amount of the traffic
being performant for the new system.
We are sort of moving towards this new release that are coming very soon,
where we have then decided to remove some of these algorithms because they're simply unused,
and Vegas is the only one currently that is left.
We will continue to tune on these things.
We will learn as more clients are coming on, as we do various upgrades in the network,
so we would likely have to tune different parameters.
And the entire system is made so that the directory authorities,
which is the nodes that are sort of the trust anchor in the Tor system,
will be able to tune certain parameters based on various ideas or experiments we want to try out.
So all of this sounds good, and many people will sort of say,
"Okay, is this then going to be super performant, or how is it actually going to change things?"
As some of you may know, we have had a denial of service going on on the network for quite a while,
so I'm trying to show this using some fairly old plots,
and then show it with some very current plots after the network has upgraded to the 047.
So if you look at this one, this is the time to complete a 5 MB download
to a public server over the Tor network.
As you can see, the variance is very, very high in this.
We have some error conditions where it took up to 50 seconds for these requests to go through,
and most likely the user will have abandoned the web request that was happening there.
So after we deployed congestion control, it now looks like this.
We're down to having sort of a 20 second boundary on this,
and it's starting to look a whole lot better,
and you will likely also experience this when you're using Tor browser in your daily life,
because ideally the request should go through quickly, right?
I believe there's a lot of you in this room, or in this stage, that is operating Tor relays.
A massive thank you to everybody who upgraded to 047 very, very quickly.
Yes, big round of applause for that.
It is so important that when we get releases out, that they get deployed to the network,
because many of the releases that we make requires us to upgrade the network,
before we can start upgrading the clients.
So before we can start including these features in, for example, Tor browser,
or other applications that use this Tor, then we need the network to be upgraded.
So huge thanks to everybody who's been doing this.
I think last week, I've been camping for a while,
but last week we released the release candidate for the Tor 048.
Just like with 047, which had the congestion control feature,
there's some pretty cool features that we have in there.
The congestion control feature, there's some pretty important features
that I'll be talking about in a moment, which is coming out in this release.
So we really hope that people will be very, very snappy with upgrading quickly again,
so we can start testing these things out on the live network.
So one of the big features that we are adding in 048 is very much related
to this denial of service attacks that we've seen.
The nature of the denial of service attack is not so that there is one denial of service attack.
We've likely seen many different kinds of attacks that's happening within the network.
But because of the design in Tor, we can't really go in and say,
and pinpoint what exactly is happening,
but we know that some of the attacks is happening towards onion service traffic,
which means that it stays within the network and never goes out over the exit nodes.
So one thing we've implemented is that we have implemented a proof of work scheme.
Some of you know these from blockchain projects and how they are burning down our planet.
This system is designed in a way so that by default it's not enabled,
but the onion service, if it sort of realizes that it's under attack
on various network conditions, seems bad.
It can enable it and slowly sort of increase the
difficulty that is used for clients to connect.
We have chosen a scheme that we got help from from a contributor called Tiverdoor.
Thanks to them for working on this.
If you are interested in sort of the technical details about how this scheme works,
we have this proposal called 327, which includes all the technical aspects for how to implement it.
And as of last week, I believe, we also have the documentation ready if you are operating onion
services for how to use this feature and testing it out in your production system.
There is one slight catch with this proof of work scheme.
It uses quite a lot of memory,
which means that particularly for Apple's very closed iOS platform,
we are likely not going to be able to enable it.
It's Guardian Project who is doing the ORBOT for iOS.
And because of Apple's network extension memory limits,
we are very unlikely to be able to support it there.
But the effect will likely be the same as if the feature was not there,
namely that if there is an error condition happening for the given onion service,
then the client will simply not be able to reach it.
And this will just impact iOS users more.
If you know anybody who works for Apple, then please ask them to bump this limit.
It has been bumped a few times, but it's still a bit too low for us at least.
The big feature that is going to come in 048 is a feature called conflux.
Historically, most people in here is probably aware of that when you have a torrent circuit,
you have a decline which connects to a guard node and you extend it to a middle node and
then finally to an exit node where you then make your TCP flows out to the internet.
One of the API features that we have now inside of Tor from the congestion control system
is that we can get information while the traffic is being sent and received
on how congested the link is.
This allows us to utilize this conflux feature to create multiple legs into the network
and sort of rendezvous at the exit node.
And then the client can learn which of these two paths through the network is the least
congested and switch over to transmit and receive on that one.
So hopefully, now that we have seen with the congestion control part that we have gotten
the variance of errors and delays down, then we hope with conflux we'll see sort of a greater
performance when you're downloading larger things and using the Tor network in general.
One of the really nice things with this whole performance project we've been running in the
network team for a while now has been how the team has been working together and developing
things.
We have historically used this tool called Chutney.
It's sort of a little Python thing where you can say give me a Tor network with 400
nodes and it then starts 400 Tor instances on your computer and you can test things.
We also have a system called Shadow which is like a more powerful simulator where you
can sort of simulate a whole Tor network and including having time change.
So we can, for example, simulate a year's use of the Tor system over like a couple of
hours and we can even do it in our CI tool chain which has been really, really awesome.
One really nice thing with sort of how we work, we work like many research projects.
So we get grants to do our work.
Often these denial of service conditions that happen have this impact that we need to drop
everything we're currently doing of deliverables and switch over to doing like mitigating the
attacks.
We fortunately now have a sponsor where we can do some of this work on denial of service
if something comes up and if you need to tune things or if we need to come up with new
mitigation techniques.
For people who are sort of nerding out on our GitLab, then these things are tracked as
like GitLab has this label thing and we have a denial of service label and we also have
a sponsor 112.
So if people are interested in seeing what kind of things we are planning, you can go
look there.
How many people in here have heard of RD?
Okay, not so many.
RD is our attempt, hopefully it's going to be successful, with trying to write a Rust
implementation of Tor that will eventually replace the C implementation.
One of the issues that exists with C Tor is it's a very old application by now that has
sort of evolved over time.
The architecture of it is not really fit for sort of the modern day world, how we do
applications, how we have mobile applications and so on.
So RD will become primarily an API for working with different kind of Tor objects like our
D network documents and making circuits and these kind of things.
And it will eventually allow you to both build a Tor binary like you're used to having today
where you can connect over a SOX port, but it will also allow you to have a Tor implementation
embedded into your applications if you want to do certain things.
And finally, it will also of course support onion services.
We - it's not an easy decision to make that you want to rewrite, like throw away so many
years of work and then try to rewrite it in another language.
We do some assessment on our issues.
When we have issues that we consider that they have such severity that they would be
considered security bugs.
And we could see at some point that 21 out of 34 of what we call troves, they're a bit
like our internal CVEs where we have some different categories that we use, would be
highly unlikely to happen if we were using more memory safe languages such as Rust.
Another big component of this is that the network team at Tor is much more excited about Rust
than they are with C and developer happiness is fairly important as well.
If we look a bit at the roadmap for RD, we are now at the point where we are working on onion
services.
We've just entered the year two funding for this.
There's already stuff that if people want to try around with having sort of a little
Rust library where you can build onion services, then you can start trying it out today.
The goal is that when we are at the end of this year, the browser team at Tor will be
start to be able to play around with embedding RD into the browser.
We are currently working on getting funding for building relays and bridges and directory
authorities and all these sort of things that are hosting the network.
But for now we are sort of focusing on the client side because the way Tor is designed,
the client side is sort of the difficult thing to build.
Right now it's almost the majority of the network team at Tor is working on RD or RD
related deliverables.
We also have a little VPN project that we are experimenting with that is also getting
some attention.
We hope to very soon have sort of the entire team focusing on this.
We are currently three people out of ten, I think, that is sort of left focusing on
C Tor.
What you will most likely see is that we will start limiting client features, so only do
the things that is needed to upgrade the network and then do the client features primarily
in RD itself.
One of the big things we want to work on soon is UDP, for example.
UDP will have a network upgrade in the C Tor implementation and then it will have
client feature support only existing in RD.
We will of course continue to support C Tor until we are ready to replace it.
It would be crazy to do anything else.
If you are interested in tracking some of these engineering efforts that we are doing,
I believe that one of the nice things we have with RD is that it will probably be easier
for more people such as yourself to contribute.
The C Tor codebase was a bit difficult to get, sort of wrap your head around when you
were just diving into it.
We have an RSC channel, Tor Dev, on the OFTC network and we also map it over to Matrix
as Tor Dev.
We have our GitLab account, well, our GitLab instance where you can track the engineering
efforts and what we are doing and so on.
If any of you are interested in this, you are also welcome to come and find me here at
camp and talk a bit about these things.
Now I'm going to pass the mic to Juga who is going to talk a bit about bandwidth scanning.
So, bandwidth scanners, we need them to monitor the Tor network performance, to better distribute
the load across the network and to help to verify relays bandwidth.
Because the relays themselves report the bandwidth they see that pass through them, but there
are no other relays to verify them, to verify that.
So, how it works.
The scanner builds two hub circuits between the relay that wants to measure and another
relay that helps to measure this relay with double bandwidth.
Then the load data through this circuit and write it in a file.
Every hour, this file is read by the director authorities and they vote on the consensus
with.
This is a graph of the number of relays measured by the bandwidth scanner by each directory
authority in the last four days.
What is new now is that we have also a bridge scanner.
The bridge scanner works in a very similar way, but it creates three hubs circuit.
This helps with the users to have a better experience because now, instead of just distributing
the bridges that are available, the bridge authority is distributing the bridges that
which bandwidth ratio is over a certain threshold.
This is a graph about the measured bridges in the last days.
The ones that were accepted over that ratio and the ones that are not.
Then Gecko is going to talk about more network health things.
Thanks.
Looks good.
You heard already from Alex and Hugo a lot about the performance angle of network health work.
As you might know, there are many more things we have to consider once we want to think
about whether a network is in a healthy state or not.
We have a project Alex has been mentioning already which we are currently focused on,
which is trying to defend more effectively against malicious relays, which is a considerable
issue for the Torrentburg for a long time.
You might have heard about this.
You can see the details in the blog post I wrote a while ago.
Having malicious relays in the network is definitely not good for the health of the
network overall.
What we want to do is improving the state of the art which is currently deployed and which
we currently have as tools.
That is only one of the things which needs improvements.
As we have seen over the years of fighting malicious relays, setting on having more and
more sophisticated tools to find and hunt down and kick out malicious relays is not going
to fly over the long run.
There is no way to win this arms race in that way.
We have to have a kind of a social approach as well, a different tool in our tool chain
for defending against malicious relays that way.
Gus will talk a bit about that, what we have in mind and what we plan in the next couple
of weeks and months.
But that is an important thing to keep in mind.
There is no technical only solution against malicious relays in the Tor network.
We are working on that part, getting this right.
The other important point when you are thinking about network health is that there are a lot
of relay attacks which we have seen over time over the years in practice and in papers.
We never found time to actually address those in our day-to-day work.
We got funding for that.
I will talk a bit later about what those attacks are we have in mind.
Alex mentioned one, which is a really hard one.
Because we have seen in this year four different attacks coming to the network at the same
time and all four of them would have needed totally different approaches to tackle them.
One, Alex mentioned already the proof of work thing and there are other ones.
But we want to make progress on those things as well in this upcoming work.
The timeline for the project was October 22 to October 24.
We are kind of in the middle of where we are with the work on this part.
We have to dig a bit deeper.
It is not just fixing tools for detecting malicious relays or fixing those attacks.
We have to redo our matrix pipeline as well.
The reason for that is, as I said, it is not really enough to have tools for detecting
malicious relays and then kicking them out.
Sometimes we have seen really persistent attackers in the network doing attacks over a month
and sometimes one or two years.
So we need to detect those things earlier.
And we need to do those detections by not having only compressed tables of descriptors
and consensus and whatnot over a month and years as we have it now.
Because that is really cumbersome to work with and slowing things down.
So what we want to do is we want to redo our matrix pipeline in a way, as you can see on
this picture here.
So we have a downloader which is downloading all the different descriptors and then macro
descriptors and consensus.
And it is writing things in an archive and at the same time it is putting things in a
Postgres QL database and then a Victoria matrix piece which is helping with the time series.
And then we want to do a RESTful API written in REST where we can query stuff and having
some shiny Grafana dashboards where you can easily see how things are going on.
This is not just meant to be for our internal usage, but of course at the first time we
would be the ones dog fooding our stuff.
But we plan to somehow expose this to interested operators and the wider community as well
where they can dig through the data and come up with issues in the network we might not
see and just play with stuff around at some point later.
You see how this goes.
At the second point we want to do while we are working on this project in the matrix
area is we want to build a small service to annotate our knowledge of the tool network
and this tool is called TagTool.
And it is basically like a relay search we have right now.
If you go to matrix.toolproject.org there is an option to look at the state of your
relays via a relay search.
And what you want to do here is we want to add a little node or category to tool routers
where we can keep kind of state of tool routers which would for instance say hey, maybe Gus
knows the operator or maybe I am knowing the operator or maybe Roger knows the operator
and maybe you can annotate and say hey, I have met this guy at the camp or at DefCon
or whatever.
So we can see a bit first how many of the operators we actually know.
Because nobody is knowing this nowadays.
And then we can ask, I know these number of operators and we can think about how many
of the capacity of the network do I actually know by operators.
This kind of stuff.
And this allows us later on to put actually tools for our bad relay work on top of that.
Gus mentioned some of those.
One thing that got mentioned in the past is we could say okay, in order to minimise the
risk for our users, we could just cap the total amount of exit capacity a single operator
can run in the network.
Right now it is not really a thing embedded in the code.
It is kind of operators contacting us and saying hey, I am now running 10% of the exit capacity,
is that okay or should I maybe do something else?
Because it might be exposing too much risk to your users.
But then we could think about building a thing, maybe say okay, maybe it is just allowed for
exit operators to run 5% of the exit capacity or maybe just 10 or whatever.
But first of all we need to know how many of those folks we actually know to have an
idea of how many people we trust in the network by now.
So for the relay attacks, here are some of the things we could think about and we are
actually thinking about.
You can find more details in this milestone where we have a detailed description of the
things we want to work on and managing those attacks.
There are really side channel attacks we have seen in the past where users got de-anonymised,
you want to investigate and finally fix tagging attacks, where we try to manipulate the routes
of the network users can use, not be, but attackers can use and we try to defend that.
And those attacks are already mentioned.
We have some traffic analysis papers, resistance papers seen in the past and we want to implement
the most promising things from them into the code we have.
And then there are bandwidth inflation attacks.
You might recall Huka talking about the bandwidth scanner.
One of the ideas was at some point building a bandwidth scanner, which is actually not
really only measuring the bandwidth, but detecting once relays try to claim they are able to
relay more traffic than they actually are.
Because there might be people around saying, oh, I just set up this relay and whenever
a user is coming, I just give it a really crappy service trying to minimise the cost
I have for running a relay, but once the bandwidth scanner is coming and measuring my relay,
I show there is a really big bandwidth I have available and that's why I get a higher consensus
rate which means more users are picking my router in the circuit.
And this kind of cheating and attacking the network you want to avoid at some point.
And there are ways we can do that actually and we are working in this project moving
forward in this direction.
So I think that's it for me.
I pass the mic to Gus for the final part.
[Applause]
Hello.
So this is a Tor exit node that is hosted here in CCC camp.
Thanks, Article 10, for her running this relay.
So I'm going to talk a little bit about the work that the Tor community team is doing.
The thing that we need to acknowledge is that Tor as an organisation, we developed the software.
As you see Alex talking about the complex stuff, about conflux, congestion control,
algorithms, Geekoo and Hugo talking about network health.
But there is a very important component that is the community who is running the software.
Like without relay operators we don't have Tor network or we don't have Tor.
So the idea of this, to mitigate the attacks against Tor, the idea is to improve the network
health or the community health of the Tor network.
So we talked before on building tools to fight bad relays like creating scanners and this
kind of stuff.
This is one way to fight bad relays but the other way is also using the social approach.
So instead of running scanners, this is also what we are going to do, but the idea is to
have a community that we know.
So we can say, oh, this person that is running 100 relays, we know them and they are cool
people.
So the idea is to make the community harder for infiltration.
So one quick question.
Please raise your hand if you are running a Tor node.
Okay.
I can see some people.
So according to our specialist on Twitter, called X, the NSA controls a significant amount
of Tor nodes.
Something like 90%.
I don't know how accurate is this.
I heard the day steps.
Nothing is truly safe.
So according to this random person on the Internet, 90% of people here are paid or part of NSA.
And this is ridiculous.
So we can see part of the network health discussion on the Internet is very low.
People do claims about who is running Tor relays and this is something that we want
to change.
Not about the reputation but also about knowing the community, showing the work that people
are doing is also rewarding.
People want to be seen like, hey, I'm contributing with the Tor network, 10% of the exit capacity
or 15% of the exit capacity.
And this is very important.
So there are many adversaries against Tor, but I believe there are two extreme positions
that are not helpful in this debate.
One is underestimating the problem.
Like well, everything is fine.
Please don't remove my super sketch relays.
They are just happy relays.
So we have this kind of attitude.
And the other one is like overestimation of the problem.
Like oh, well, the CIA is running the whole Tor network, so I'm going to use this other
solution here instead of the Tor network.
And this is obviously a good solution.
So one thing that we have been working to mitigate this problem of trust on the Tor
network is to create a process involving the relay operators.
Hello?
Is it working?
Okay.
So we have a process involving the Tor community.
So the idea is to have relay operators to submit proposals or ideas or comments or suggestions
how we can improve the Tor network and how we can improve the health of the Tor network.
We wrote recently a policy where you can understand how is the process, how you can submit a proposal
to improve the Tor network health.
So some examples of proposals.
First thing, first example, guideline for consensus that Geco was talking here.
Another thing was allowing allow limit consensus as a fraction by family.
So if you are running a family of nodes, you can only run 10% of the capacity.
No matter what, if you add 100 more relays, it will always be the same.
This is a proposal, it's not approved.
We are evaluating just kind of ideas.
And also we have another proposal, another example of proposal of how you can conduct
open source investigation when you're hunting malicious relays.
So one thing, one problem that we sometimes we have, people report that a relay is bad,
but when we ask them, okay, how that relay is bad, what they are doing, the person doesn't
explain how they came up with that result.
So if we cannot reproduce that thing, we cannot say that's a bad relay.
And if you look, for example, in Twitter and social media and other places, you can see
sometimes people saying crazy stuff about exit nodes or relays, saying like well, this
is clearly malicious because you can see by the contact info.
And sometimes relay operators are very funny people.
They sometimes create names of their associations as CIA about confidential integrity and authentication.
So sometimes people are very funny and users are not, they don't think that's a funny thing.
So this is why we have the guideline to have, to help people to do open source investigation.
So because Tor network is a public network, we should expect that people are checking
their relays and see the behaviour of these relays.
Another example of a proposal that was recently submitted from the community, like we have
a limit of how many relays you can run by IPv4.
So before was true.
And the idea was you cannot run with one single IPv4 address.
You cannot run 1,000 relays.
So to avoid this kind of attack, it was limited to two.
We bumped that number to four because some relay operators wrote a very nice proposal
saying hey, the IPv4 is very expensive and we have hardware, we have capacity, we have
bandwidth.
The only thing that we don't have and very expensive is to buy IPv4.
So the idea was okay, we can bump to four and see how the attackers are going to act,
what is their behaviour.
If everything is fine, we can bump to eight.
So right now you can see that we have, you can run eight relays per IPv4.
And that created a very interesting graphic here.
You can see that before this proposal, we were like 1,500 relays, as it is known, sorry.
And now after this proposal was approved, we have now almost 2,500 relays.
So this is how a policy made by the community and enforced by the project, just how we can
change the network.
So sometimes we believe how we are going to increase the capacity, how we are going to
make more people to collaborate or make the network faster.
Sometimes it's not an engineer thing but also a policy thing.
Like something that we can change on the Tor code, something we can change on the Tor network.
So the next activity that we have here in the camp, tomorrow we have the Tor relay operator
meet up.
You don't need to be running a relay to join this meet up.
If you are interested in Tor, if you have questions about Tor or Snowflake or other
plugable transports that we didn't talk about today, you are welcome to come and ask about
this.
It's going to be on Burn Hack Village at 4pm.
You can also check this very cool project from Article 10 on their village.
I don't know how to pronounce it in German so I'm not going to pronounce it.
And you can check their exit notes and make questions.
Article 10 is one of the top, one of the largest exit operators on the Tor network.
So if you think like, oh, NSA is running a bunch of relays, actually it's probably Article
10, nothing to hide, that's the operator for Netherlands, many other operators here in
Germany.
So you have opportunity here to, I believe, meet 40% of the Tor exit capacity.
So if you walk around and talk with people, you are running the Tor network.
And we have another campaign happening with the Electronic Fund Foundation called the Tor
University Challenge.
It's diversity but means education.
So if you have a school, if you have an education project, you can join this challenge.
The idea is to have more universities running relays.
And you can see on this website how many universities are running relays.
And if you want to be part of the Tor community, like running relays, there are other ways
to contribute with the Tor project, like doing trainings, translation, et cetera.
But you can also join as an operator.
We have a mailing list that's open and you can subscribe.
We have the Tor forum.
It's a very easy tool for newcomers to join and ask questions.
We have a matrix and IRC to chat with us.
And we have monthly online meetups that are announced on the Tor relays mailing list.
But if you cannot run a relay, you can also run a Zoomflick proxy.
Again, we have more than 141,000 proxies of Zoomflick, which is very important right now
for people in Iran to access the free and open Internet.
And to run a Zoomflick proxy is very easy.
You need to install an add-on on your browser and you can help people.
And yeah, and very curious that Germany is also the top largest country contributing
with Zoomflick proxies.
So again, thank you for running a bunch of Zoomflick proxies.
And I think that's it from me.
A great round of applause for this tour through Tor Networking.
We now have an open mic.
You can queue up here for a few questions.
So if you have a few questions, please queue up back around the back, please.
Start running through the camera.
Hey, thanks for your talk.
I really do see that the attacks on the network are a big problem.
And I find the extra layer of social layer of trust you want to implement interesting.
I can see a few problems with that.
But I mainly wonder if it might undermine the spirit of Tor, the spirit of anonymity,
if I have to identify as a relay operator to you, especially in a country where to operating
might be illegal.
Thank you.
Hello.
Oh, here.
Okay, yeah.
So this is a great question about the transparency and privacy.
The Tor network requires user privacy, and who operates the Tor network, we require transparency.
It doesn't mean that we require phone number, identification, legal names, your passport
number.
We don't require that.
We require like a nickname and some way to contact you.
So we are not requiring your to disclose your legal identity to the Tor project or something
like that.
And this is very important because we wrote recently a document about that, like the Tor
relay expectation for Tor relay operators, which we say running a Tor relay requires
transparency.
So if you cannot do that, maybe running a relay is not the best way to contribute with
the Tor network.
Maybe it's running a training, maybe it's localizing Tor, maybe it's teaching others
about Tor, so you don't expose yourself to the Tor network because the Tor network is
a public network.
So if you are at risk, maybe you should not run a relay.
Thank you for these insights into Tor development.
Thank you for being here.
And I think we can find you somewhere.
If we have further questions, find them.
Thank you.
[APPLAUSE]
[MUSIC PLAYING]
(music ends)